Enlightenment is release from samsara.
(Sunim) Hello.
(Audience) Hello.
(Sunim) In Buddha's teaching,
Happiness is getting what we want.
We smile and feel pleasure,
Suffering is not getting what we want.
We frown and feel pain.
So, the pain and pleasure cycle repeats
in our lives.
What do we call this? We call this
samsara, the cycle of rebirth.
The unenlightened human beings keep going
through this cycle of rebirth.
To the unenlightened, the pain is
suffering and pleasure is happiness.
But from a broader perspective,
the repetition of pain/pleasure cycle
is the suffering.
Suffering is being unable to escape from
the repeated cycle of pain and pleasure.
Escaping from suffering is
not changing pain to pleasure.
It is escaping from this repetition of
pain and pleasure cycle, samsara.
This is called enlightenment.
This is called nirvana.
So, the happiness we pursue is
choosing pleasure instead of pain.
The way of Buddha in his teaching,
in short, nirvana is
Being released from
the endless cycle of rebirth.
So, when we pray for what we want,
even if we get everything we asked for,
We are still living in samsara.
We just have
a few more pleasure than pain.
But we still have not been released
from the samsara.
Asking for blessings in prayers is
like planting a seed for samsara.
From the point of enlightenment,
any religion that prays for blessings is
Planting seeds of samsara.
That is not the way to enlightenment.
Then, what is the way to Enlightenment?
We move toward Enlightenment
by way of Practice.
This Buddhist practice is the meaningful
and correct way to pray.
Praying for blessings
only plants seeds of samsara,
So it's not the proper way
to practice Buddhism.
So if prayer means
getting what we want, then
the word "prayer"
should not be used in Buddhism.
Is that original intention of prayer,
getting what we want? No.
Is that original intention of religion?
No.
Religion means the highest teaching
in Chinese Characters.
What is the highest teaching, then?
It teaches us how to be happy, to be free,
to be the masters of our own lives.
If you pray to the mighty
to get what you want,
are you a master or a servant?
You are a servant.
In certain religion,
people vow to be servants.
They say I am so and so's servant.
In Buddhism,
no matter how great Buddha is,
our goal is not to be his servants.
Our goal is to be like him.
So walking the path to enlightenment is
what we call practice.
So, when we use the word "pray"
in this context, how should we pray?
We pray from the perspective of practice.
We pray to be
on the pathway to enlightenment.
We can't get to
the pathway to enlightenment
by praying 'please do this for me'.
(Sunim) When there are high waves,
enjoy the waves.
When it's calm, enjoy the calm.
But, we like calm ocean, not rough ocean.
We can even fall into
the waves and struggle.
The ocean has its appeal
when there are big waves, right?
I have never done this but
The windsurfers like the high waves
or the low ones?
They like the high waves.
Most people are apt to drown
in high waves, but
the windsurfers prefer the high waves
and enjoy them more.
So, would they go to the high waves
or low waves for windsurfing?
They prefer high waves.
It's not easy finding
a spot with calm waves.
a spot with big waves, either.
In the past, people would avoid the places
with high waves, but the windsurfers,
Would search for the spots with big waves.
And those places become their playground.
Depending on our need,
we choose different things.
So, we ought to choose the practice
and follow its path.
This is called discipline. A person with
self-discipline moves forward.
Can we achieve this at once
or do we need to keep trying?
We have to keep trying continuously.
So, we say, "we just do it!"
We cannot achieve this quickly.
We need to try again whenever we fail.
In spite of failures, we stand firm
on the ground with eyes towards our goal.
We take one step at a time
and become Buddhist practitioners.
If we only focus on our goal,
we become impatient.
We become pessimistic.
"I just can't do this."
Is this what you get
after all these years of practice?'
we would criticize ourselves and others.
What if we settle in the present
without any further efforts?
I'm not the only one who gets angry.
You get angry too.'
Everyone is like that'
We would rationalize like that.
We need to accept the difficulty
of the practice in the present,
but at the same time,
move forwards towards our goal.
Even though it's not going well, compared
to the days before we started the practice
We have come a long way, have we not?
Yes. we have.
We look back and say,
“I've come a long way”
and encourage ourselves.
We look forward and say,
“I still have a long way to go”
and get up and keep going.
But those who focus on the goal only,
would get discouraged.
thinking,
“Is this all I can achieve in ten years?”
Those who look back the starting place
would become complacent and say
“This is good enough”.
These are both extremes.
We have to look at both where we started
and where we are going.
Being able to see both here and there,
this and that, front and back,
high and low ...
We call this insight, wisdom.
We don't lean one way or the other
because we see both sides.
So we keep practicing
without being discouraged.
We haven't gotten there yet,
but we don't get distressed.
We are getting better than before,
but we don't stop. We don't get arrogant
(Sunim) So this is the way to practice.